Guide to the Carl W. Ackerman Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Carl W. Ackerman Papers
1910-1962.
Ackerman, Carl W. (Carl William), 1890-1970.
3.75 linear ft. ( 9 boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0007
4078388
History
Carl William Ackerman (1890-1970), Columbia University B. Litt. 1913, was Dean of the Columbia University School of Journalism from 1931 to 1956. He spent from 1960 to 1962 researching and writing a biography (unpublished) of Hokan Bjornstrom Steffanson, 1883-1962, the Swedish-American industrialist and financier.
Ackerman was a champion of freedom of the press. His professional career was forged in both major World Wars. While working as a correspondent in World War I with the United Press, Ackerman came to attention when he published Germany, The Next Republic?, a book that discussed the possibility of a successful democracy in post-Kaiser Germany. When the book was printed in 1917, at the height of World War I, this sentiment was considered quite radical. The London Times Literary Supplement commented: "For the serious student of affairs the importance of the book lies in the large mass of information which it contains as to the struggle which was going on all the time in Germany between the two great parties, the Pan-Germans and the party of comparative moderation which centered round the Foreign Office."
Mexico's Dilemma was considered "topical," "limited in scope and subject," and of "little relevance." Trailing the Bolsheviki was similarly received. As a biography, Dawes, the Doer was panned as "poorly handled," whereas Biography of George Eastman was called by the New York Tribune "objective in the sense that it holds strictly to the drama of events in justification of its hero. This makes it eminently readable, even exciting at times, purely as an epic of success achieved, a sort of `Pilgrim's Progress' of business."
Mr. Ackerman was an outspoken advocate of a journalism foundation in the United States "dedicated to the study of the daily newspaper and government." He explained, "We need scientific studies of the press by the press, and for the press, which will contribute to the progress of journalism as the great educational foundations have advanced medicine."
Ackerman married Mabel VanderHoof in 1914, and was the father of Robert VanderHoof Ackerman.
Writings by Ackerman: Germany, the Next Republic?, Hodder & Stoughton, 1917.; Mexico's Dilemma, Doran 1918, Gordon Press, 1976; Trailing the Bolsheviki, Scribner, 1919; Dawes, the Doer (biography), Houghton, 1930; Biography of George Eastman, Houghton, 1930. Ackerman authored numerous articles, pamphlets, and reports on journalism and related affairs.
Scope and Content
Research notes, transcripts of interviews with Steffanson, correspondence, clippings, and other biographical materials deals with all aspects of Steffanson's life including his early career in America after 1909, the Swedish and Canadian paper, wood pulp, and cellulose industries, cultural and social life and New York real estate in the 1920's, his excape from the "Titanic" in 1912, and genealogical notes on the family of his wife, Mary Pinchot Eno.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 4 series
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
eries II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Books
Series IV: Research Notes and Interviews
Subjects
Ackerman, Carl W. (Carl William), 1890-1970.; Dawes, Charles Gates, 1865-1951.; Dodge, M. Hartley (Marcellus Hartley), 1881-1963.; House, Edward Mandell, 1858-1938.; Kahn, Otto Hermann, 1867-1934.; Keir, Malcolm.; Latimer, S. L. (Samuel Lowry), 1891-1975.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948.; Scully, Frank, 1892-1964.; Sherwood, Robert E. (Robert Emmet), 1896-1955.; Steffanson, Hokan Bjornstrom, 1883-1962.; Eno, Mary Pinchot.; Watts, Harvey Maitland, 1864-1939.; Willert, Arthur, Sir, 1882-; Wiseman, William, Sir, b. 1885.; Papermaking--Canada.; Papermaking--Sweden.; Wood-pulp industry.; Oral histories
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-9. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
1980 Papers Ackerman, Douglas V. (estate of) Gift
Gift of the Estate of Douglas V. Ackerman, 1980.
Related Material
For edited transcript of interview see Steffanson, Hokan Bjornstrom, Oral history interview, 1965.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Dawes, Charles Gates To Carl William Ackerman Chicago, 28 March 1951 (Box 1)
    (1 page, typed letter signed)
  - Dodge, Marcellus Hartley To Carl William Ackerman New York, 10 September 1947 (Box 1)
  - House, Edward Mandell To Carl William Ackerman New York, 17 September 1927 (Box 1)
  - Hillyer, Robert Silliman To Carl William Ackerman Cambridge, Mass., 10 May 1934 (Box 1)
  - Kahn, Otto Herman To Carl William Ackerman New York, 31 August 1925 (Box 1)
  - Keir, Malcolm To Carl William Ackerman Hanover, N.H., 12 February 1929 (Box 1)
  - Latimer, Samuel Lowery, Jr. To Carl William Ackerman Columbia, S.C., 20 December 1950 (Box 1)
    (2 page, typed letter signed)
  - Pershing, John Joseph To Carl William Ackerman Washington D.C., 25 January 1952 (Box 1)
  - Scully, Frank To Carl William Ackerman on board the S.S. Rex, 15 August 1933 (Box 1)
    (1 page, autograph letter signed)
  - Sherwood, Robert Emmet To Carl William Ackerman [n.p.], 3 May 1949 (Box 1)
  - Watts, Harvey Maitland To Carl William Ackerman Philadelphia, 1 July 1919 (Box 1)
  - Willert, Sir Arthur To Carl William Ackerman [London], 15 December 1953 (Box 1)
    (4 page, autograph letter signed)
  - Wiseman, Sir William George Eden To Carl William Ackerman New York, 10 December 1953 (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - Letters to Carl William Ackerman from various people, 1942-1959 (Box 1)
    (8 letters)
- Series III: Books
  - Inscribed books from his library (Box 1-2)
- Series IV: Research Notes and Interviews
  - Research notes on H.B. Steffanson (Box 3-5)
  - Research notes on H.B. Steffanson & transcripts of notes and interviews (Box 5-9)